<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept xml:lang="en-us" id="ctoolsijcomref15645">
<title>ij SQL command behavior</title>
<prolog>
</prolog>
<conbody>
<p>Any command other than those documented in the <codeph>ij</codeph> command reference
are handed to the current connection to execute directly. The statement's
closing semicolon, used by <codeph>ij</codeph> to determine that it has ended, is
not passed to the underlying connection. Only one statement at a time is passed
to the connection. If the underlying connection itself accepts semicolon-separated
statements (which <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> does not), they can be passed to the connection
using <codeph>ij</codeph>'s Execute command to pass in a command string containing
semicolon-separated commands.</p>
<p><codeph>ij</codeph> uses the result of the JDBC execute request to determine
whether it should print a number-of-rows message or display a result set.</p>
<p>If a JDBC execute request causes an exception, it displays the <i>SQLState</i>, if any, and error message.</p>
<p>Setting the <codeph>ij</codeph> property <i><xref href="rtoolsijpropref25589.dita#rtoolsijpropref25589">ij.showErrorCode</xref></i> to <i>true</i> displays the <i>SQLException</i>'s error code (see <xref href="rtoolsijpropref29864.dita#rtoolsijpropref29864"/>).</p>
<p>The number-of-rows message for inserts, updates, and deletes conforms to
the JDBC specification for any SQL statement that does not have a result set.
DDL (data definition language) commands typically report "0 rows inserted/updated/deleted"
when they successfully complete.</p>
<p>To display a result set, <codeph>ij</codeph> formats a banner based on the JDBC <i>ResultSetMetaData</i> information returned from <i>getColumnLabel</i> and <i>getColumnWidth</i>. Long columns
wrap the screen width, using multiple lines. An <i>&amp;</i> character
denotes truncation (<codeph>ij</codeph> limits displayed width of a column to 128
characters by default; see <xref href="rtoolsijcomref12281.dita#rtoolsijcomref12281"/>).</p>
<p><codeph>ij</codeph> displays rows as it fetches them. If the underlying DBMS
materializes rows only as they are requested, ij displays a partial result
followed by an error message if there is a error in fetching a row partway
through the result set.</p>
<p><codeph>ij</codeph> verifies that a connection exists before issuing statements
against it and does not execute SQL when no connection has yet been made.</p>
<p>There is no support in <codeph>ij</codeph> for the JDBC feature multiple result
sets.</p>
</conbody></concept>
