<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "../dtd/reference.dtd">
<reference xml:lang="en-us" id="rtoolsdblookoptions">
<title>dblook options</title>
<prolog>
</prolog>
<refbody>
<section><p>The <codeph>dblook</codeph> utility options include:</p></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-z &lt;schemaName&gt;</dt>
<dd>
<p>specifies the schema to which the DDL should be restricted.  Only
objects with the specified schema are included in the DDL file.</p></dd></dlentry>
</dl></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-t &lt;tableOne&gt; &lt;tableTwo&gt; ...</dt>
<dd>specifies the tables to which the DDL should be restricted. All tables
with a name from this list will be included in the DDL file subject to <codeph>-z</codeph> limitations, as will the DDL for any keys, checks, or indexes on
which the table definitions depend.
<p>Additionally, if the statement text
of any triggers or views includes a reference to any of the listed table names,
the DDL for that trigger/view will also be generated, subject to <codeph>-z</codeph> limitations.
If a table is not included in this list, then neither the table nor any of
its keys, checks, or indexes will be included in the final DDL. If this parameter
is not provided, all database objects will be generated, subject to <codeph>-z</codeph> limitations. Table names are separated by whitespace.</p></dd></dlentry>
</dl></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-td</dt>
<dd>specifies a statement delimiter for SQL statements generated by dblook.
If a statement delimiter option is not specified, the default is the semicolon
(';'). At the end of each DDL statement, the delimiter is printed, followed
by a new line.</dd></dlentry>
</dl></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-o &lt;filename&gt;</dt>
<dd>specifies the file where the generated DDL is written. If this file
is not specified, it defaults to the console (i.e. standard System.out).</dd></dlentry>
</dl></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-append</dt>
<dd>prevents overwriting the DDL output ('-o' parameter, if specified) and "dblook.log"
files.  If this parameter is specified, and execution of the <codeph>dblook</codeph> command
leads to the creation of files with names identical to existing files in the
current directory, <codeph>dblook</codeph> will append to the existing files. If
this parameter is not set, the existing files will be overridden.</dd></dlentry>
</dl></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-verbose</dt>
<dd>specifies that all errors and warnings (both SQL and internal to <codeph>dblook</codeph>) should be echoed to the console (via System.err), in addition
to being printed to the "dblook.log" file. If this parameter is not
set, the errors and warnings only go to the "dblook.log" file.</dd></dlentry>
</dl></section><section>
<dl>
<dlentry><dt>-noview</dt>
<dd>specifies that CREATE VIEW statements should not be generated.</dd></dlentry>
</dl></section>
</refbody></reference>
