<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN"
 "../dtd/reference.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<reference id="rrefsqljcreatesynonym" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>CREATE SYNONYM statement</title>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>CREATE SYNONYM statement</indexterm><indexterm>Synonyms<indexterm>creating</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<refbody>
<section><p>Use the CREATE SYNONYM statement to provide an alternate name
for a table or a view that is present in the same schema or another schema.
You can also create synonyms for other synonyms, resulting in nested synonyms.
A synonym can be used instead of the original qualified table or view name
in SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE or LOCK TABLE statements. You can create
a synonym for a table or a view that doesn't exist, but the target table or
view must be present before the synonym can be used.</p><p>Synonyms share
the same namespace as tables or views. You cannot create a synonym with the
same name as a table that already exists in the same schema. Similarly, you
cannot create a table or view with a name that matches a synonym already present.</p><p>A
synonym can be defined for a table/view that does not exist when you create
the synonym. If the table or view doesn't exist, you will receive a warning
message (SQLSTATE  01522). The referenced object must be present when you
use a synonym in a DML statement.</p><p>You can create a nested synonym (a
synonym for another synonym), but any attempt to create a synonym that results
in a circular reference will return an error message (SQLSTATE 42916).</p><p>Synonyms cannot be defined in system schemas. All schemas starting with 'SYS' are considered system schemas and are reserved by <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>.</p><p>A synonym cannot
be defined on a temporary table. Attempting to define a synonym on a temporary
table will return an error message (SQLSTATE XCL51).</p></section><section><title>Syntax</title><codeblock><b>CREATE SYNONYM <xref href="rrefsynonymname.dita#rrefsynonymname">synonym-Name</xref> FOR { <xref
href="rrefviewname.dita#rrefviewname">view-Name</xref> | <xref href="rreftablename.dita#rreftablename">table-Name</xref> }</b></codeblock>The <xref
href="rrefsynonymname.dita#rrefsynonymname">synonym-Name</xref> in the statement represents
the synonym name you are giving the target table or view, while the <xref
href="rrefviewname.dita#rrefviewname">view-Name</xref> or <xref href="rreftablename.dita#rreftablename">table-Name</xref> represents
the original name of the target table or view.</section>
<example><title>Example</title>
<codeblock><b>CREATE SYNONYM SAMP.T1 FOR SAMP.TABLEWITHLONGNAME</b></codeblock>
</example>
</refbody>
</reference>
