<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN"
 "../dtd/reference.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<reference id="rrefdeclaretemptable" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>DECLARE GLOBAL TEMPORARY TABLE statement</title>
<shortdesc>The DECLARE GLOBAL TEMPORARY TABLE statement defines a temporary
table for the current connection. </shortdesc>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>DECLARE GLOBAL TEMPORARY TABLE statement</indexterm>
<indexterm>tables<indexterm>temporary</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm><indexterm>SQL
statements</indexterm>DECLARE GLOBAL TEMPORARY TABLE</indexterm></keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<refbody>
<section><p>These tables do not reside in the system catalogs and are not
persistent. Temporary tables exist only during the connection that declared
them and cannot be referenced outside of that connection. When the connection
closes, the rows of the table are deleted, and the in-memory description of
the temporary table is dropped.</p></section>
<section><p>Temporary tables are useful when: <ul>
<li>The table structure is not known before using an application.</li>
<li>Other users do not need the same table structure.</li>
<li>Data in the temporary table is needed while using the application.</li>
<li>The table can be declared and dropped without holding the locks on the
system catalog.</li>
</ul></p></section>
<section><title>Syntax</title> <codeblock><b>DECLARE GLOBAL TEMPORARY TABLE <i><xref
href="rrefdeclaretemptable.dita#rrefdeclaretemptable/tempcoltablename">table-Name</xref></i>
    { column-definition [ , column-definition ] * }
[ ON COMMIT {DELETE | PRESERVE} ROWS ]  
NOT LOGGED [ON ROLLBACK DELETE ROWS]
 </b></codeblock></section>
<section id="tempcoltablename"><title>table-Name</title><p>Names the temporary
table. If a schema-Name other than SESSION is specified, an error will occur
(SQLSTATE 428EK). If the schema-Name is not specified, SESSION is assigned.
Multiple connections can define declared global temporary tables with the
same name because each connection has its own unique table descriptor for
it.</p><p>Using SESSION as the schema name of a physical table will not cause
an error, but is discouraged. The SESSION schema name should be reserved for
the temporary table schema.</p></section>
<section id="tempcolcolumndef"><title>column-definition</title><p>See <xref
href="rrefsqlj30540.dita#rrefsqlj30540"></xref> for <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> for
more information on <codeph>column-definition</codeph>. <codeph>DECLARE GLOBAL
TEMPORARY TABLE</codeph> does not allow <codeph>generated-column-spec</codeph> in
the <codeph>column-definition</codeph>.</p></section>
<section id="rreftemptabledatatype"><title>Data type</title><p>Supported data
types are: <ul>
<li>BIGINT</li>
<li>CHAR</li>
<li>DATE</li>
<li>DECIMAL</li>
<li>DOUBLE</li>
<li>DOUBLE PRECISION</li>
<li>FLOAT</li>
<li>INTEGER</li>
<li>NUMERIC</li>
<li>REAL</li>
<li>SMALLINT</li>
<li>TIME</li>
<li>TIMESTAMP</li>
<li>VARCHAR</li>
</ul></p></section>
<section id="rreftemptableoncommit"><title>ON COMMIT</title><p>Specifies the
action taken on the global temporary table when a COMMIT operation is performed.</p></section>
<section><title>DELETE ROWS</title><p>All rows of the table will be deleted
if no hold-able cursor is open on the table. This is the default value for
ON COMMIT. If you specify ON ROLLBACK DELETE ROWS, this will delete all the
rows in the table only if the temporary table was used. ON COMMIT DELETE ROWS
will delete the rows in the table even if the table was not used (if the table
does not have hold-able cursors open on it). </p></section>
<section><title>PRESERVE ROWS</title><p>The rows of the table will be preserved.</p></section>
<section id="rreftemptablenotlogged"><title>NOT LOGGED</title><p>Specifies
the action taken on the global temporary table when a rollback operation is
performed. When a ROLLBACK (or ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT) operation is performed,
if the table was created in the unit of work (or savepoint), the table will
be dropped. If the table was dropped in the unit of work (or savepoint), the
table will be restored with no rows.</p></section>
<section><title>ON ROLLBACK DELETE ROWS</title> <p>This is the default value
for NOT LOGGED. NOT LOGGED [ON ROLLBACK DELETE ROWS ]] specifies the action
that is to be taken on the global temporary table when a ROLLBACK or (ROLLBACK
TO SAVEPOINT) operation is performed. If the table data has been changed,
all the rows will be deleted.</p></section>
<section><title>Examples</title><codeblock><b>set schema myapp;

create table t1(c11 int, c12 date);

declare global temporary table SESSION.t1(c11 int) not logged;</b>
-- The SESSION qualification is redundant here because temporary 
-- tables can only exist in the SESSION schema. 

<b>declare global temporary table t2(c21 int) not logged;</b> 
-- The temporary table is not qualified here with SESSION because temporary 
-- tables can only exist in the SESSION schema.

<b>insert into SESSION.t1 values (1); </b>
-- SESSION qualification is mandatory here if you want to use 
-- the temporary table, because the current schema is "myapp."

<b>select * from t1;</b> 
-- This select statement is referencing the "myapp.t1" physical 
-- table since the table was not qualified by SESSION.

</codeblock> <note>Temporary tables can be declared only in the SESSION schema.
You should never declare a physical schema with the SESSION name.</note><p>The
following is a list of DB2 UDB DECLARE GLOBAL TEMPORARY TABLE functions that
are not supported by <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>: <ul>
<li>IDENTITY column-options </li>
<li>IDENTITY attribute in copy-options</li>
<li>AS (fullselect) DEFINITION ONLY</li>
<li>NOT LOGGED ON ROLLBACK PRESERVE ROWS</li>
<li>IN tablespace-name</li>
<li>PARTITIONING KEY</li>
<li>WITH REPLACE </li>
</ul> </p></section>
<section><title>Restrictions on Declared Global Temporary Tables</title> <p><ph
conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> does not support the
following features on temporary tables. Some of these features are specific
to temporary tables and some are specific to <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>.</p><p>Temporary
tables cannot be specified in the following statements: <ul>
<li>ALTER TABLE </li>
<li>CREATE INDEX</li>
<li>CREATE SYNONYM</li>
<li>CREATE TRIGGER</li>
<li>CREATE VIEW</li>
<li>GRANT</li>
<li>LOCK TABLE</li>
<li>RENAME</li>
<li>REVOKE</li>
</ul></p><p>You cannot use the following features with temporary tables:</p><ul>
<li>Synonyms, triggers and views on SESSION schema tables (including physical
tables and temporary tables) </li>
<li>Caching statements that reference SESSION schema tables and views</li>
<li>Temporary tables cannot be specified in referential constraints and primary
keys</li>
<li>Temporary tables cannot be referenced in a triggered-SQL-statement</li>
<li>Check constraints on columns</li>
<li>Generated-column-spec</li>
<li>Importing into temporary tables</li>
</ul> <p>If a statement that performs an insert, update, or delete to the
temporary table encounters an error, all the rows of the temporary table are
deleted.</p><p>The following data types cannot be used with Declared Global
Temporary Tables: <ul>
<li>BLOB</li>
<li>CHAR FOR BIT DATA</li>
<li>CLOB</li>
<li>LONG VARCHAR</li>
<li>LONG VARCHAR FOR BIT DATA</li>
<li>VARCHAR FOR BIT DATA</li>
<li>XML</li>
</ul></p></section>
</refbody>
</reference>
