<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
 "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<concept id="cdevcsecure42374" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Working with user authentication</title>
<shortdesc><ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> provides
support for user authentication and user authorization. <term>User
authentication</term> determines whether a user is a valid user. It establishes
the user's identity.
<term>User authorization</term> determines what operations a user's established
identity can perform.
You are strongly urged to implement both authentication and
authorization on any multi-user database used in production.</shortdesc>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>user authentication<indexterm>overview</indexterm></indexterm>
<indexterm>authentication<indexterm>users, overview</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<conbody>
<p>When user authentication is enabled (by default, it is <i>not</i> enabled), 
the user that requests a connection must provide a valid name and password,
which <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> verifies against
the repository of users defined for the system. After
<ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> authenticates the user
as valid, <xref href="cdevcsecure36595.dita#cdevcsecure36595">user
authorization</xref> determines what operations the user can perform on the
database to which the user is requesting a connection.</p>
<p>For user authentication, <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> allows
you to provide a repository of users in a number of different ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can use <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>'s
NATIVE authentication mechanism to store user credentials in a database. See
<xref href="cdevcsecurenativeauth.dita#cdevcsecurenativeauth"></xref> for
details.</li>
<li>You can hook <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> up to
an external directory service elsewhere in your enterprise.</li>
<li>You can create your own directory service.</li>
<li>You can use <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>'s
simple BUILTIN mechanism for creating a repository of users.
</li></ul>
<note type="important"><ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>'s
BUILTIN authentication mechanism is suitable only for development and testing
purposes, and it will no longer be documented in future releases. It is strongly
recommended that production systems rely on NATIVE authentication, an
external directory service such as LDAP, or a user-defined class for
authentication. It is also strongly recommended that production systems protect
network connections with SSL/TLS.</note>
<p>You can define a repository of users for a particular database or for an
entire system, depending on whether you use system-wide or database-wide
properties.</p>
<p>When <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> user authentication
is enabled and <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> uses
an external directory service, the architecture looks something like that
shown in the following figure. The application can be a single-user application with
an embedded <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> engine
or a multi-user application server.</p>
<fig expanse="column" id="cdevcsecure32704"><title><ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>
user authentication using an external service</title>
<image href="authentic_os.gif" placement="break"><alt>This figure shows how an application passes Derby user authentication through an external directory service before access to a Derby database is allowed.</alt>
</image>
</fig>
<p><ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> always runs embedded
in another Java application, whether that application is a single-user application
or a multiple-user application server or connectivity framework. </p>
<p>A database can be accessed by only one JVM at a time, so it is possible
to deploy a system in which the application in which <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> is
embedded, not <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph>, handles
the user authentication by connecting to an external directory service. The
application can be a single-user application with an embedded
<ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> engine or a multi-user
application server. The following figure shows this kind of deployment.</p>
<fig expanse="column"><title>Application user authentication using an external
service</title>
<image href="appauth_os.gif" placement="break"><alt>This figure shows how an external directory service provides application user authentication before access to a Derby database is allowed.</alt>
</image>
</fig>
</conbody>
</concept>
