<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
 "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<concept id="cdevadvjdbc41138" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Offering connection choices to the user</title>
<shortdesc>JDBC's <i>java.sql.Driver.getPropertyInfo</i> method allows a generic
GUI tool to determine the properties for which it should prompt a user in
order to get enough information to connect to a database. Depending on the
values the user has supplied so far, additional values might become necessary.
It might be necessary to iterate though several calls to <i>getPropertyInfo</i>.</shortdesc>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>java.sql.Driver.getPropertyInfo</indexterm><indexterm>Available
databases<indexterm>list of provided by databaseName attribute</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<conbody>
<p>If no more properties are necessary, the call returns an array of zero
length.</p>
<p>In a <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> system, do
not use the method against an instance of <i>org.apache.derby.jdbc.EmbeddedDriver</i>.
Instead, request the JDBC driver from the driver manager:</p>
<codeblock>java.sql.DriverManager.getDriver(
    "jdbc:derby:").getPropertyInfo(<i>URL</i>, <i>Prop</i>)</codeblock>
<p>In a <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> system, the
properties returned in the <i>DriverPropertyInfo</i> object are connection
URL attributes, including a list of booted databases in a system (the <i>databaseName</i> attribute).</p>
<p>Databases in a system are not automatically booted until you connect with
them. You can configure your system to retain the former behavior, in which
case the steps described in this section will continue to work. See "<i>derby.system.bootAll</i>" in
the <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#pub/citref"></ph>.</p>
<p><i>getPropertyInfo</i> requires a connection URL and a <i>Properties</i> object
as parameters. Typically, what you pass are values that you will use in a
future call to <i>java.sql.DriverManager.getConnection</i> when
you actually connect to the database.</p>
<p>A call to <i>getPropertyInfo</i> with parameters that contain sufficient
information to connect successfully returns an array of zero length. (Receiving
this zero-length array does not <i>guarantee</i> that the <i>getConnection</i> call
will succeed, because something else could go wrong.)</p>
<p>Repeat calls to <i>getPropertyInfo</i> until it returns a zero-length array
or none of the properties remaining are desired.</p>
</conbody>
</concept>
