<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN"
 "../dtd/task.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<task id="tdevcsecurenewbootpw" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Encrypting databases with a new boot password</title>
<shortdesc>You can apply a new boot password to a <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> database
by specifying the <i>newBootPassword</i> attribute on the connection URL when
you boot the database.</shortdesc>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>encrypting databases<indexterm>new boot password</indexterm></indexterm>
<indexterm>databases<indexterm>encrypting, new boot password</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<taskbody>
<prereq><ul>
<li>If the database is configured with log archival for roll-forward recovery,
you must disable log archival and perform a shutdown before you can encrypt
the database with a new boot password. </li>
<li>If there are any global transaction that are in the prepared state after
recovery, the database cannot be encrypted with a new boot password.</li>
<li>If the database is currently encrypted with an external encryption key,
you should use the <xref href="tdevcsecurenewextkey.dita#tdevcsecurenewextkey"><i>newEncryptionKey</i></xref> attribute
to encrypt the database.</li>
</ul></prereq>
<context><p>When you use the <i>newBootPassword</i> attribute, a new encryption
key is generated internally by the engine and the key is protected using the
new boot password. The newly generated encryption key encrypts the database,
including the existing data. You cannot change the encryption provider or
encryption algorithm when you apply a new boot password.</p><p>To encrypt
a database  with a new boot password:</p></context>
<steps>
<step><cmd>Specify the <i>newBootPassword</i> attribute in a URL and reboot
the database.</cmd><stepxmp>For example, when the following URL is used when
the <codeph>salesdb</codeph> database is rebooted, the database is encrypted
with the new encryption key, and is protected by the password new1234xyz:<codeblock> jdbc:derby:salesdb;bootPassword=abc1234xyz;newBootPassword=new1234xyz</codeblock
></stepxmp>
  <info>
    <p>
    If <xref href="cdevcsecure36127.dita#cdevcsecure36127">authentication</xref>
    and
    <xref href="cdevcsecure36595.dita#cdevcsecure36595">SQL authorization</xref>
    are both enabled, the credentials of the 
    <xref href="cdevcsecureDbOwner.dita#cdevcsecureDbOwner">database owner</xref>
    must be supplied as well, since reencryption is a restricted operation.
    </p>
  </info>
<info><p>If you disabled log archival before you applied the new boot
password, create a new backup of the database after the database is reconfigured
with the new boot password. For more information, see the section "Backing up
and restoring databases" in the <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#pub/citadmin"></ph>,
particularly "Roll-forward recovery".</p></info></step>
</steps>
</taskbody>
</task>
