<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
 
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN"
 "../dtd/task.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<task id="tdevcsecureunencrypteddb" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Encrypting an existing unencrypted database</title>
<shortdesc>You can encrypt an unencrypted <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> database
by specifying attributes on the connection URL when you boot the database.
The attributes that you specify depend on how you want the database encrypted.</shortdesc>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>encrypting databases<indexterm>existing unencrypted databases</indexterm></indexterm>
<indexterm>databases<indexterm>encrypting, existing unencrypted</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<taskbody>
<prereq><ul>
<li>If the database is configured with log archival, you must disable log
archival and perform a shutdown before you can encrypt the database. </li>
<li>If there are any global transaction that are in the prepared state after
recovery, the database cannot be encrypted.</li>
</ul></prereq>
<context><p>When you encrypt an existing, unencrypted database, you can specify
whether the database should be encrypted using a boot password or an external
encryption key.  You can also specify the <i>encryptionProvider</i> attribute
and the <i>encryptionAlgorithm</i> attribute on the connection URL. The database
is configure with the specified encryption attributes and all of the existing
data in the database is encrypted. </p><p>Encrypting a database is a time
consuming process because it involves encrypting all of the existing data
in the database. If the process is interrupted before completion, all the
changes are rolled back the next time that the database is booted. If the
interruption occurs immediately after the database is encrypted but before
the connection is returned to the application, you might not be able to boot
the database without the boot password or external encryption key. In these
rare circumstances, you should try to boot the database with the boot password
or the external encryption key. </p><note othertype="Recommendation" type="other">Ensure
that you have enough free disk space before you encrypt a database. In addition
to the disk space required for the current size of the database, temporary
disk space is required to store the old version of the data to restore the
database back to it's original state if the encryption is interrupted or returns
errors. All of the temporary disk space is released back to the operating
system after the database is encrypted.</note><p>To encrypt an existing unencrypted
database:</p></context>
<steps>
<step><cmd>Specify the <i>dataEncryption=true</i> attribute and either the <i>encryptionKey</i> attribute
or the <i>bootPassword</i> attribute in a URL and boot the database.</cmd>
<stepxmp>For example, to encrypt the <codeph>salesdb</codeph> database with
the boot password <codeph>abc1234xyz</codeph>, specify the following attributes
in the URL:<codeblock>jdbc:derby:salesdb;dataEncryption=true;bootPassword=abc1234xyz </codeblock></stepxmp>
<info>
  <p>
  If <xref href="cdevcsecure36127.dita#cdevcsecure36127">authentication</xref>
  and
  <xref href="cdevcsecure36595.dita#cdevcsecure36595">SQL authorization</xref>
  are both enabled, the credentials of the 
  <xref href="cdevcsecureDbOwner.dita#cdevcsecureDbOwner">database owner</xref>
  must be supplied as well, since encryption is a restricted operation.
</p>
</info>
<info><p>
If you disabled log archival before you encrypted the database, create
a new backup of the database after the database is encrypted. For more
information, see the section "Backing up and restoring databases" in the
<ph conref="../conrefs.dita#pub/citadmin"></ph>, particularly "Roll-forward
recovery".</p></info></step>
</steps>
</taskbody>
</task>
