<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
 "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<concept id="cadminappsclientdiffs" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Differences between the embedded client and the network client driver</title>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>Network client driver<indexterm>differences with embedded
driver</indexterm></indexterm></keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<conbody>
<p>The following are known differences that exist between the <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> embedded
driver and the network client driver. Note that there may be undocumented
differences that have not yet been identified. Some differences with the network
client may be changed in future releases to match the embedded driver functionality.<ul>
<li>Error messages and SQLStates can differ between the network client and
embedded driver. Some SQLStates may be null when using the network client,
particularly for data conversion errors.</li>
<li>Multiple SQL exceptions and warnings will only return the SQLState of
the first exception when using the network client. The text of the additional
exceptions will be appended to the text of the first exception. See <xref
href="radminapps811974.dita#radminapps811974"></xref>.</li>
<li>Treatment of error situations encountered during batch processing with java.sql.Statement, java.sql.PreparedStatement and java.sql.CallableStatement is different. With the embedded driver processing stops when an error is encountered; with the network client driver processing continues, but an appropriate value as defined in the java.sql.Statement api is returned in the resulting update count array.</li>
<li>To use an encrypted user id and password, you need to have the IBM's Java
Cryptography Extension (JCE) Version 1.2.1 or later.</li>
</ul></p>
</conbody>
</concept>
