<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
 "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<concept id="cadmindbintegrity" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Maintaining database integrity</title>
<shortdesc>One of the most important responsibilities of a database
administrator is to maintain the integrity of the database and prevent it from
becoming corrupted.</shortdesc>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords><indexterm>corruption<indexterm>avoiding</indexterm></indexterm>
<indexterm>database corruption<indexterm>avoiding</indexterm></indexterm>
<indexterm>data integrity<indexterm>maintaining</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata></prolog>
<conbody>
<p><ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> must be able to sync
to disk. Some machine, disk, or operating system settings can prevent a proper
sync and cause unrecoverable database corruption in the event of a power
failure, system crash, or software crash. To avoid database corruption, you can
do the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do not enable disk write caching on the hard drive that holds the database.
Disable write caching if it is turned on (it is enabled by default on many
Windows systems). Disk write caching can increase operating system performance.
However, it can also result in the loss of information if a power failure,
equipment failure, or software failure occurs. Consult your operating system
support documentation for information on how to disable disk write caching.</li>
<li>Run <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> on a local
drive rather than on an NFS mounted, SMB mounted, or other network mounted
disk.</li>
<li>Disable any other settings or options that might prevent a proper sync to
disk when <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> is writing
its transaction logs or other data.</li>
</ul>
<p>Many corruption issues can arise from improper backups or restores. Back up
your database in a way that prevents it from becoming corrupted:</p>
<ul>
<li>Always make sure the database is shut down or frozen before using operating
system commands to back it up.</li>
<li>Always back up the database to a fresh location rather than overwriting
any existing data.</li>
</ul>
<p>After you perform a backup, check the consistency of the database. See
<xref href="cadminconsist01.dita#cadminconsist01"></xref> for details.</p>
<p>See <xref href="cadminhubbkup98797.dita#cadminhubbkup98797"></xref> for more
information.</p>
</conbody>
</concept>
