<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept xml:lang="en-us" id="ctuntransform25868">
<title>Flattening a subquery into an EXISTS join</title>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords>
<indexterm>Subqueries<indexterm>flattening of to an EXISTS join</indexterm></indexterm>
<indexterm>EXISTS join<indexterm>definition</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<conbody>
<p>An EXISTS join is a join in which the right side of the join needs to be
probed only once for each outer row. Using such a definition, an EXISTS join
does not literally use the EXISTS keyword. <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> treats a statement
as an EXISTS join when there will be at most one matching row from the right
side of the join for a given row in the outer table.</p>
<p>A subquery that cannot be flattened into a normal join because of a uniqueness
condition can be flattened into an EXISTS join if it meets all the requirements
(see below). Recall the first example from the previous section (<xref href="ctuntransform36368.dita#ctuntransform36368"/>):</p>
<codeblock><b>SELECT c1 FROM t1 WHERE c1 IN (SELECT c1 FROM t2)</b></codeblock>
<p>This query could not be flattened into a normal join because such a join
would return the wrong results. However, this query can be flattened into
a join recognized internally by the <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> system as an EXISTS join.
When processing an EXISTS join, <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#prod/productshortname"></ph> knows to stop processing the right
side of the join after a single row is returned. The transformed statement
would look something like this:  
<codeblock><b>SELECT c1 FROM t1, t2
WHERE t1.c1 = t2.c1
EXISTS JOIN INTERNAL SYNTAX</b></codeblock></p>
<p>Requirements for flattening into an EXISTS join:   
<ul>
<li>The subquery is not under an OR. </li>
<li>The subquery type is EXISTS, IN, or ANY. </li>
<li>The subquery is not in the SELECT list of the outer query block. </li>
<li>There are no aggregates in the SELECT list of the subquery. </li>
<li>The subquery does not have a GROUP BY clause. </li>
<li>The subquery does not have an ORDER BY, result offset, or fetch first
clause.</li>
<li>The subquery has a single entry in its FROM list that is a <xref href="ctuntransform13966.dita#ctuntransform13966/rtuntransform41494">base table</xref>. </li>
<li>None of the predicates in the subquery, including the additional one formed
between the left side of the subquery operator and the column in the subquery's
SELECT list (for IN or ANY subqueries), include any subqueries, method calls,
or field accesses. </li>
</ul></p>
<p>When a subquery is flattened into an EXISTS join, the table from the subquery
is made join-order-dependent on all the tables with which it is correlated.
This means that a table must appear inner to all the tables on which it is
join-order-dependent. (In subsequent releases this restrictions can be relaxed.)
For example:   
<codeblock><b>SELECT t1.* FROM t1, t2
WHERE EXISTS (SELECT * FROM t3 WHERE t1.c1 = t3.c1)</b></codeblock></p>
<p>gets flattened into  
<codeblock><b>SELECT t1.* FROM t1, t2, t3 WHERE t1.c1 = t3.c1</b></codeblock></p>
<p>where <i>t3</i> is join order dependent on <i>t1</i>. This means that the possible join orders are (<i>t1</i>, <i>t2</i>, <i>t3</i>), (<i>t1</i>, <i>t3</i>, <i>t2</i>), and (<i>t2</i>, <i>t1</i>, <i>t3</i>).</p>
</conbody></concept>
