<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- 
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at      

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0  

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software  
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,  
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and  
limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "../dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept xml:lang="en-us" id="ctun_xplain_tables">
<title>Understanding XPLAIN style database tables</title>
<prolog><metadata>
<keywords>
    <indexterm>XPLAIN style</indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<conbody>
    <p>
        XPLAIN style is an enhanced form of RUNTIMESTATISTICS processing
        which preserves captured statistics information in database tables.
        Once the statistics have been collected and saved in the 
        tables, they can be queried for analysis purposes.
    </p>
    <p>
        Rows accumulate in the SYSXPLAIN_* database tables until you 
        empty the tables by dropping them or executing DELETE FROM statements
        against them.
    </p>
    <p>
        Note that, although these tables have stylized names which all
        start with the prefix "SYSXPLAIN_*", they are not in fact special
        system catalogs, but are merely ordinary database tables, which
        can be accessed in all the standard ways that any other database
        table is accessed. The tables are automatically created if they
        are not present when statistics are being captured. The tables
        are all located in a particular schema which is specified by the
        <codeph>SYSCS_UTIL.SYSCS_SET_XPLAIN_SCHEMA()</codeph> system procedure.
    </p>
    <p>
        The XPLAIN style database tables are summarized here. For more
        information about the structure and content of each table,
        see "XPLAIN style tables" in
        the <ph conref="../conrefs.dita#pub/citref"></ph>.
    </p>
    <dl>
        <dlentry>
        <dt>SYSXPLAIN_STATEMENTS</dt>
        <dd>This table contains one row for each statement which
            has had statistics captured. This row contains the text of the
            statement, as well as identifiers which can be used to join with
            the other tables to find more data about how this statement was
            executed.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
        <dt>SYSXPLAIN_RESULTSETS</dt>
        <dd>This table contains one row for each result set which
            was used during the execution of a particular explained statement.
            Most queries have one or several result sets; some complex queries
        can have many result sets.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
        <dt>SYSXPLAIN_SCAN_PROPS</dt>
        <dd>This table contains one row for each result set which
            performed a scan of a table, index, or constraint. Using the
            information in this row, you can determine how much data needed
        to be examined by the scan.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
        <dt>SYSXPLAIN_SORT_PROPS</dt>
        <dd>This table contains one row for each result set which
            performed a sort of data. Using the information in this row, you
        can determine how much data needed to be sorted.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
        <dt>SYSXPLAIN_STATEMENT_TIMINGS</dt>
        <dd>This table contains timing information at the statement
            level. Timing information is optional, but if it is captured, the
            data in this table can be used to determine how much time each
        statement took.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
        <dt>SYSXPLAIN_RESULTSET_TIMINGS</dt>
        <dd>This table contains timing information at the result set
            level. Timing information is optional, but if it is captured, the
            data in this table can be used to determine how much time each
        result set took.
        </dd>
        </dlentry>
    </dl>
</conbody></concept>

